I think it's-- Ah, perfect. That's a little too loud, maybe.
All right, we're going to get started in this, what appears to have become
cavernous space. A couple quick announcements before we get started.
One,
many of you may have known the illustrious Henry Engledow, who passed away
very recently. We will be
reserving a few minutes during our business meeting for people who would like to
share a remembrance. Also, at the registration table, beginning tomorrow and
remaining through the end of the week, there will be a book for his family and
loved ones if you'd like to sign or write some remembrances in there. That's first.
Second, at the end of the day today, please don't forget to be at City Hall
promptly. "Promptly" was the nice way that they worded it,
so please be on time for that. That is not in here.
It is at City Hall, which is across the way.
Also, for those of you who may have some location challenges periodically in your
lives, this is the only day that we're here at the Aula.
The rest of the week, we'll be at the Oslo Congress Center.
So please do not come back here unless you're feeling contemplative and want to
look at the paintings.
That's starting tomorrow morning.
Also, for any of you that have questions about Whova or need corrections in
Whova, please don't email us individually.
It's a challenge to check our individual accounts, so don't do that.
Please email the conference organizers' email.
That's
conf-organizers@tadwig.org. So if you have
any issues with Whova, please contact us that way.
And then finally,
just want to take an opportunity to call out our hosts here in Oslo
and recognize them. Those are the folks from the Norwegian Biodiversity Information
Centre, the University of Oslo, the Natural History Museum, and GBIF Norway.
So if anybody is from those organizations, could you embarrass yourself and stand
up just for one moment? Come on now.
So not only have they been involved in the planning since the beginning of this,
but there are bunches of students and others who are running around with those blue
T-shirts as volunteers. So please be kind and thank them for their
efforts.
So we'll get going. So a taste of TADWIG is what is next.
And so I will invite our organizer of the session, the convener extraordinaire,
and past chair of TADWIG, Ellie Wallace.
So welcome to our Taste of TADWIG session.
So we've got a more rapid-fire set of presentations this afternoon.
So each talk and questions, if there's time, will take up 15 minutes.
And the talks were specially chosen to provide a taste of the conference topics and
streams that have emerged around the theme of research and robot-ready biodiversity
data standards. That's the one lovely thing about having this set-up that we do of
starting off with symposia and then getting talks to fill those symposia, plus
getting the contributed orals presentations being put forward, is that the
themes sort of emerge organically from what gets
given to us. So we've got a really broad range of interesting themes that have come
out for this conference. So we hope you enjoy this smorgasbord of tasty conference
bites. And we're going to
start the session with the foundations that the field is built on, the literature.
So several of the speakers today have already shown us excerpts of letters,
digitized books, and journals, and there'll be a strong set of symposia and
workshops related to literature throughout the conference.
Our first speaker, Nicole Carney, will remind us of the importance of literature
with her talk about the Biodiversity Heritage Library. Thanks, Nicole.
Thank you, Ellie. Hello, everyone.
It is a great honor to be speaking in this beautiful room at TADWIG in what is an
incredibly significant year for the Biodiversity Heritage Library.
Those of you who have been following along will know that we have been on a
precarious and uncertain journey.
Last year, we were thrown into the wilderness, and we have had to find our own way
out. This beautiful illustration is from Joseph Hooker's 1854 Himalayan
journals. It's a living bridge. It is formed from the aerial roots of fig trees,
and for me, it really captures where BHL is right now.
For the past 18 months, we've been building a new bridge for BHL.
It is holding us up for now. We've put down some strong roots, but there are gaps.
BHL could still fall, and we don't yet know what is on the other side, which is
both scary and exciting. Today, I'm going to tell you the story of how we've got
this far and what it still might take to get to the other side.
Now, I know most in the room are very familiar with BHL because it is essential to
your work. But for those who aren't, the Biodiversity Heritage Library is the
world's largest virtual library of open access biodiversity literature and archival
material, and one of the world's most critical resources of biodiversity knowledge.
It is a global consortium of 684 contributing organizations and libraries who have
together made over 64 million pages of biodiversity knowledge freely accessible
online. It contains information on millions of the world's species and is the
foundation of our understanding of biodiversity.
BHL exists because the cultivation of natural science cannot be efficiently carried
on without reference to an extensive library, and the extensive library on BHL
contains information and resources produced as early as the 1100s and as recently
as last month.
Every page is fully searchable. Our taxonomic name recognition allows you to search
for both current and past scientific names.
We have added article data to over 450 scientific articles, and over 80,000
of those now have DOIs, bringing those articles into the modern linked network of
scholarly research. We retrospectively assign DOIs to species descriptions
published centuries ago, all the way through to the current day.
This is a DOI BHL assigned to a species description that was published in November
last year. To give you a sense of the massive amount of information made accessible
and discoverable on the Biodiversity Heritage Library, this is a map produced by
Rod Page. Every single dot on this map represents a latitude and a longitude pair
in a scholarly article on BHL.
However, this important discoverability work and our work assigning DOIs and many
other BHL projects were put on hold last year when we were thrown into an emergency
mode, when we received the unexpected news that the Smithsonian Institution, our
administrative and technical home, would cease to host the BHL on the 1st of
January this year. This decision placed BHL, one of the world's most widely used
and longest-running biodiversity infrastructures, at risk.
We were completely at sea, with the very real possibility of being pulled under.
As our host, the Smithsonian had provided the BHL secretariat staff and the
technical team, as well as the seven servers required to run the BHL website and
the website itself. With this support gone, we had to act quickly if we were to
help keep BHL afloat. We formed an emergency and transition team, and together with
the BHL Executive Committee, we have worked tirelessly over the past 18 months to
build a more autonomous, global, and sustainable BHL.
At this point, back in April last year, we had no idea what we were going to do,
how we would gather the support we needed to continue, or what the future of BHL
might look like. So it was more important than ever for us to communicate openly
and honestly with our community, to say that we didn't yet know what we were going
to do, we didn't have the answers, to invite their ideas and support, and to
reassure them that we would do everything we could to save the BHL and its staff.
We communicated every stage of the transition across our blog and on social media,
and we started a community forum on Discourse to invite their ideas and concerns.
The threat to the BHL encouraged an overwhelming outpouring of appreciation
and panic from our users. These included comments like, "BHL is one of the most
important, most valuable online projects and one of the greatest collections on the
internet. It is an indispensable record of the earth's biodiversity and represents
an invaluable part of our scientific and cultural heritage.
It's an absolutely vital resource for ecologists and evolutionary biologists." This
was my favorite, a pledge from a user.
She says, "I will send a box of handmade cookies every year for the rest of my life
to whichever institution takes on the BHL."
In June last year, we opened a global call for support, inviting expressions of
interest from institutions and stakeholders to host BHL's operational and technical
roles and services. In August, we moved to a new financial and legal home, the
Council on Library and Information Resources.
This means that BHL is now independently able to accept donations, pursue grants,
and manage our own staff contracts. It also provide BHL with autonomy.
BHL is no longer constrained by a single US federally affiliated
university, no longer constrained by their requirements and shifting priorities.
We're now operating as an independent, globally governed consortium.
BHL's call for support invited offers of technical hosting,
support for our existing systems, and some start funding.
What we received is giving us stability for one to two years.
I want to really emphasize this. BHL is secure and only secure
through to 2027.
On the 1st of January, BHL officially moved across to its new independent chapter.
On the left is our blog post explaining what that means for BHL and its staff, and
in February, we shared the exciting news that we have secured the staff positions
of all existing staff.
During this time, we have been extremely grateful to our BHL members.
These are the organizations who govern BHL and whose membership fees, along with
those of our affiliates, provide BHL with a reliable source of support.
Three of those organizations, the University of South Florida, Vanderbilt
University, and Zenberg Nature Support, joined BHL during the transition.
At the most uncertain time in BHL's history, these organizations decided that we
were worth supporting and joining.
Two of those organizations are providing BHL with significant technical support.
The University of South Florida Libraries are providing significant system support
from the core,
BHL's metadata collection workflow system, for three years, while Vanderbilt
University is providing us with an associate cloud engineer.
Rahul Sharma joins the technical team in BHL in February, and his role will help
build a resilient modern technical foundation for BHL.
But the news that most excited our users was that the Field Museum would take over
the hosting of BHL's website and technical infrastructure.
This was the news that answered the question that was most asked by our users
during the transition, which was, what is going to happen to the BHL website?
The response was an outpouring of relief and gratitude from across the world.
It was the best news. That the incredible free, open treasure trove of nature and
the crown jewel of biodiversity literature had been saved.
And from my favorite user, "I now know where to send cookies."
That big move from Washington, DC, to Chicago was completed at the end of June and
marked the final piece of our transition away from the Smithsonian.
With BHL's immediate future becoming more stable, we were finally able to start
thinking beyond survival to the future of BHL's aging platform.
Critical part of this process was to ask our users what they most wanted improved.
In July, we ran a BHL user survey, and the message was clear.
Enhanced text search was our users' number one priority, followed by image search
and an improved page viewer.
Our BHL platform modernization project is now underway, and it's much more than a
technical upgrade. The goal is to replace BHL's legacy infrastructure with a modern
cloud-based platform that has better search and discovery, improved performance and
reliability, and data that is connected, machine actionable, and easier to find,
reuse, and connect through better APIs, linked data, and persistent identifiers.
Alongside this work, we have some really exciting new collaborations underway,
including a major project led by the Natural History Museum in London.
The NHM team is developing new ways to unlock biodiversity literature at scale, and
they're in the final stages of recruiting a data scientist dedicated to this
project. Here is who will be speaking more about this exciting work tomorrow in our
BHL symposium. Encourage you to come along.
We've also expanded the BHL executive committee, adding a strategic development
officer and a member at large, which will increase our capacity for fundraising,
partnerships, and long-term planning.
David Eagleman, our chair, and our new strategic development officer, Amanda Bozar,
are both here at tADWIG this week. Please do go and talk to them.
Building this new future has also made us realize that BHL needs a more diverse and
resilient funding base. At the end of 2025, we ran a targeted campaign called Give
BHL Wings, calling on our users to help BHL take flight by the 1st of January.
We set a target of $50,000 US, and we reached that goal on New Year's Eve, which
totally made my year.
Our plea also reached the media. In June this year, The Guardian published a major
feature on BHL, bringing BHL and the very real threat to its future to a much wider
audience. We saw an immediate spike in our public donations, which brought in more
than $10,000 US on the day that article was published.
We were blown away by messages of support and calls to save the extraordinary BHL.
One reader suggested that if you're a tech billionaire or even just a millionaire,
you could do something extraordinary.
So if you do know one, please send them our way.
BHL had never had to rely on public fundraising before this.
Now we do, and the response has been amazing.
Last week, just in time for tADWIG, our online public donations reached $100,000
US, more than 1,750 individual donations from 48 countries,
demonstrating how deeply individuals value BHL.
This includes more than $2,200 US per month in recurring donations.
Our current campaign, Become a BHL Sustainer, is trying to increase that reliable
ongoing support. If you can afford a cup of coffee every week, please do join our
BHL Sustains program.
2026 does not only mark the beginning of BHL's new chapter, it is also BHL's 20th
anniversary. Happy birthday, BHL.
One of the ways we're celebrating this huge milestone is by showcasing the
extraordinary breadth and history of BHL's collections and the people and the
institutions that make BHL possible.
Each post in this series celebrates the incredible treasures.
Each one has been selected by a member of our community.
So of course, they include rare books and historic field diaries.
But they also showcase the treasure between the covers, such as the article data
that makes our species descriptions discoverable.
And our most recent post celebrates BHL as a repository of information about
extinct species. I encourage you to check them out and follow along as our series
unfolds through our anniversary year.
We've come a long way across this bridge.
Last year, there were times when we genuinely did not know if BHL would have a
future. Today, we have a new foundation beneath us, new partnerships, new
possibilities, new funding streams, new grants in the pipeline, and an
extraordinary network of people and organizations holding us up.
But I cannot stand here in front of you and say that BHL's future is secure.
It isn't. We need to stop taking BHL for granted.
A living bridge becomes stronger as more roots reach out, grow, intertwine, and
together strengthen the whole. BHL now has the independence and autonomy to welcome
ideas, partnerships, collaboration, and possibilities.
So if you or your organization has expertise, resources, funding, or connections
that could help make BHL stronger, please do reach out.
BHL's future is not yet fixed, and that's what makes this time so exciting.
We will be exploring BHL's future opportunities and possibilities throughout this
week at tADWIG. Tomorrow afternoon, we have two back-to-back sessions and a
dedicated BHL symposium where we'll explore some of those new partnerships,
infrastructure, and ideas that are already reimagining and transforming BHL.
And on Thursday, we have a hands-on workshop where we'll be exploring new
approaches and tools to maximize the value of the Biodiversity Heritage Library.
We invite you to join and help build VHL's future. Thank you for listening.
We do have a minute for a question, if anyone has one.
Or you can come and find Nicole later.
Or come to our symposium or our workshop. I'll be there.
Excellent. Thank you, Nicole.
So, that was a powerful reminder that even our most trusted and beloved
infrastructures still need constant care and reinvention.
But building strong foundations is only half the story.
We also need to get the data moving fast enough to matter.
So our next speaker, Quentin Groom, will talk about exactly that,
reducing the lag between observing something and being able to act on it.
Thank you, Quentin.
Thank you, Ellie, and thank you for inviting me to speak here.
It's a wonderful opportunity. Yes.
So we make an observation, and how long does it take before someone can actually
act on it? And that's what I wanted to discuss with you in my 15 minutes.
Just to make us completely clear, I think probably most people know in here, if you
look at things like GBIF,
this is a graph of the monthly observations globally in GBIF.
You see the seasonal peaks, you see the exponential rise, and you see it drops off
a cliff over the last two years because people haven't stopped making observations.
They've just not mobilized their data yet.
And, well, why does that matter?
Hold on. I should mention one thing.
If you go back and ex--
Yeah, go back. And you extrapolate this up, you see this exponential growth, and
you can kind of estimate how much that lag really is.
It's obvious in the last couple of years, but in actual fact, it goes back quite a
number of years, probably because people are still doing their PhDs and haven't
published their data, or their herbarium hasn't published its data and things like
this. So it's quite a long thing and accounts for tens of millions of observations
as well.
So I'm interested in invasive species. A lot of my group work on invasion biology.
And any invasion biologist will know that you need to act on something quickly to
have any chance of eradicating it.
But there's other people working on biodiversity who are interested in things like
pests, diseases, disease vectors, which don't want to work on the risks of two
years ago, but want to work on the most up-to-date data as possible.
But even if you're working in conservation, there's very little point, as we often
seem to be, just charting the decline in species, when we actually want to find out
which species are declining and act on them immediately and do something about that
decline.
So what often happens with biodiversity observations now is informal
networks supply information. I see a gray squirrel in Brussels,
and I email my friend who I know works on management of invasive species.
I thought I saw a gray squirrel in Brussels.
It may have been a red one, but I'm not really sure.
And he writes to somebody else, "Maybe it was a gray squirrel," and then somebody
who kills gray squirrels goes out and does something.
And that works quite well at a local level, but it doesn't really scale.
The other issue that's coming very rapidly is that although most of our
observations on places like GBIF are created by humans,
it's not going to be very long, it may be five years, that will get overtaken by
all the data that's coming in from eDNA, from camera traps, from acoustic sensors,
automated imaging, et cetera. And without that human in the loop, any invasive
species in those data that are not being specifically looked for will just be not
seen.
So we have to find ways to alert people to invasions.
So that normally happens by the species arriving.
There's then a lag for detection. That then has to be reported.
That needs to be alerted to all the people who need to do something, and then
somebody goes out in the field and does something.
Meanwhile, the species isn't just sitting there waiting to be killed.
It establishes, it gets stronger, it spreads, and all the time, the costs of that
eradication or management get higher and higher until it actually becomes not
effective to be able to eradicate something. So where does all the time go?
Well, it takes time to observe sometimes.
Camera traps sit in the field for months with just an SD card picking up data.
There's another lag on identification that I'll talk a bit about in a second.
Digitization is often an issue with things like collections.
A lot of work goes into then standardizing data that have been collected in all
sorts of different ways, and validating that data, again, takes time.
And ultimately, there's time associated with publication.
Then, even after publication, people making alerts have to aggregate data.
They analyze the data to find the important parts of it.
They then send out alerts to the people who need to know, and action has to be
taken.
Oops, I skipped. So just taking one of those lags, the
identification. These are data from iNaturalist, where I looked at how long does it
take for
a identification to become stable. So the top line, the blue line, is birds.
Most of the time, about 50% of the time,
the identification put on that bird is correct straight off as soon as someone puts
it into iNaturalist, and then it takes several months, even years, before it gets
close to its final point. Other taxa, the next one down are the mammals, the next
one down are the insects, and right at the bottom are all the plants.
Only 10% go in as the right identification right on day one, and it takes months
before they reach an identification.
So this is a problem,
but this is a problem that identification is just difficult, and it's more
difficult for difficult-to-identify things.
Remote fieldwork means there's a built-in lag because of the difficulties, and
taxonomic uncertainty builds in difficulties and builds in lags we find it hard to
deal with. But there are also operational choices which are really a choice and
not difficulties. Data sitting around doing nothing,
people putting embargoes on data, systems aren't connected, so you can't publish
easily from them, and waiting till a dataset is finished, whatever that
means.
So
traditionally and still, we collect data, we identify it, we clean it, we validate
it, analyze it, and we publish.
But just like iNaturalist, just to some extent like our herbarium, although it
doesn't work perfectly, what is better is to observe, to publish, to improve, to
update, to improve, to update, to improve, to update continuously.
What we don't necessarily have are ways to communicate with people that this is the
raw data and this is getting better and this has been checked, and things like
this, but we do have mechanisms to do this, and this allows users to get immediate
access to data.
If you're working on invasion biology, it doesn't matter if you have a few false
positives. It matters if you have a lot of false positives, but you can do
something with those data, and you can make a decision about whether you want to
act on it.
In our One Stop project, we are building a GBIF alert system.
This is the work of Nico Nooy from the
Binary Forest. That's his name, his company, probably. He's the programmer of this.
If you're interested in invasion species alert, you can follow that QR code there
and go to the website and take a look.
This is open source code, and it allows people to build on top of GBIF a system
that will alert people however they want to be alerted to whichever species they're
interested in over a particular area they're interested in, and they can receive
customized alerts on the invasive species they have.
And I think Walter Kock is here. He's just made a system
for Norway doing this. I don't think it's public yet.
But if you're interested in this and want to find somebody who's actually a user of
this, I think he's somewhere in the room
So we heard this morning a nice introduction to the seven shortfalls that beset
large-scale knowledge on biodiversity by Hortet et al.
And I'm going to be rather bold by suggesting that they missed one,
that is rival, because over 2,000 people who have cited this paper, and as you
probably know, it's a very well-used paper.
But they don't define a distinct shortfall associated with the timeliness.
And I would argue that we aren't understanding biodiversity if we're only looking
at biodiversity that was several years old.
Timeliness is an important shortfall in what we do on work on biodiversity.
So I would define that as a delay between the biodiversity observation being made
and that information becoming accessible to be able to act on it.
I got even bolder by naming that, and as any taxonomist knows, putting a
name on something helps to have a conversation about it.
And so I'm suggesting, and I've got to pronounce her name right, Wangari Maathai,
is to be named after. She was a Kenyan zoologist.
She won the Nobel Peace Prize, I guess, just here.
And she was the founder of the Green Belt Movement.
But she recognized that people in Kenya had information on the environmental
decay in their area. She was also a politician, and she recognized the need to
listen to these people, to get the data moving from those people to the people who
could actually act on it. And so I suggest we have a shortfall for the
timeliness of biodiversity data so that we can go out there and specifically work
on shortening that timescale. So to summarize, publish soon, publish
often, and improve continuously would be my mantra.
I think people are taking photos. I should stop and let you take them.
If you're interested to read a bit more, we produced a
policy brief over the summer. Many of the people involved in this policy brief are
sitting here before you. The QR code will also take you there.
And you can see the logos of the projects up there that we're working on this.
B³ is just finished. Biodiversity Means Data is very much going on, and Neil is
sitting just there to support that.
One Stop on Invasive Species is very much behind this.
MAMBO, I think it's finished as well.
Garden is finished, and AURORA is still going on.
So I need to thank all my contributors.
There have actually been a very large number of contributors to this in all sorts
of different ways, and that's why I've listed all the projects and collaborations
below. And thank you very much for your attention.
You bet. So Quentin was quite quick, as he says.
So there's lots of time for questions if anyone has something that they would like
to challenge him with. Ramona.
We'll just get you a mic, Ramona.
I think the mic doesn't-
They can't
hear without a mic.
Want the mic?
Have we got the microphone anywhere? The roving mic?
Can we call out there and stand up there?
Yeah.
Sure. Oh, no, there it is. It's up the back.
We can call out there.
Ellie, can you run up the back?
Fine.
So pick up.
Thanks, Quentin. Great talk. So, I have occasionally recently advocated for getting
rid of the scientific publication and just publishing data directly.
Do you think that that would-- Again, I assume the answer is yes, but correct me if
I'm wrong. Wouldn't that help speed up the time to data discovery if people would
just publish their data as soon as they were available rather than waiting until a
paper's published?
This is such a big question.
Yeah, I'm frequently reminded that PhD students need a career afterwards, and so
they are nervous about releasing all of their data.
And I think to some extent, yeah, we need to detach that data collection to
some extent from the research question.
It's actually a waste of time for a PhD student to be out in the field sometimes
just collecting data. I should rephrase that a bit because I think it's very good
that PhD students are out in the field.
Not because I want them to waste their time, but because they become more connected
to life, and see what their system is.
But sometimes, data collection should be
a whole discipline of its own.
Yeah, but you're essentially advocating for a change in the value system already,
so this is just taking it another percent.
Yes.
Anyone else?
Oh, okay.
Congratulations to our keynote speakers for being the enthusiastic questioners.
One of the-
It's on.
It's on. Okay.
One of the mechanisms for speeding up data publishing and sort of
the not waiting until you publish everything you can possibly is
to explicitly provide value for data and through not just
attribution, but actually impact on other publications and
not just in form of citations, but literally for, in some cases, financial direct
contribution to the data sources.
And there are
mechanisms that are being built now to do that, mostly driven by industry for
nature data valuation, but it actually can work for other.
What are your thoughts on using those mechanisms to speed up data access
and alleviate this thought, say, you haven't published everything I could do from
those yet?
Yeah. I'm not sure I fully follow, but yeah, it doesn't make sense in the
current system that you have grants for three years and you spend that money on
data collection just for those three years, and we don't have this long-term
funding for infrastructures to collect data.
And obviously, you know about the neon data that is long-term collection.
And we certainly have movements towards that in Europe, to have infrastructures for
long-term data collection on biodiversity.
Yeah, what are my thoughts on that? There's just so much.
I would say we're still stuck on trying to observe everything, and that we need to
focus. I think even though AI and
automated systems will overtake human beings, we definitely need all those human
being observations too, because they really fit an important niche.
But we have to get much better at our indicators,
and because we know what indicators we want to follow, we know what data collects
in the first place. But then we also have the issue of the unknown unknowns, and
that's where I think the human beings really come into play, is because I don't
think AI yet is very good at the unknown unknowns.
It just kind of tends to ignore them.
I don't think that answered your question, but
We can talk about it later. All right. Thank you, Quentin. Thank you.
So we've had a reminder about the cost of delay,
but then there's the other bit in there about the need to identify
things. What is it? It's one thing to collect all that data, but do you know what
it is? And then how do you get it into
an infrastructure like GBIF or the Atlas of Living Australia, where I work?
So Pam Cameron Sluiter, who's our next speaker, is going to take us inside one of
the biggest untangling jobs in biodiversity informatics, which is to rebuild a
national taxonomic backbone. Welcome, Pam.
Hi, everybody. I'm guaranteed to stuff up the slides, so I'll just get that out of
the way to start.
I'd like to begin by acknowledging the traditional owners on the lands that Simon,
my co-author, and I work on, the Ngunnawal people and
the Wurrung- were Wurundjeri people of the Kulin nation.
It always was Aboriginal land and always will be.
We wish to acknowledge their elders, past and present, and to extend that
acknowledgement to any First Nations people who might be here today.
I'll be talking today about the use of taxonomic backbones to arrange data, how
backbones require different rules to, say, taxonomic checklists,
and how the ALA's gone about improving our backbone using the ALA as an
example.
So we are the largest publicly accessible data set in Australia with over 184
million records and many thousands of users.
Since its beginning, the taxonomic backbone of the ALA has been central to how we
serve diversity data to users. Australia has a host of reasons for using a
national species list, not only because of the high level of endemism in our biota,
but also because there are differences in the taxonomy that we Australians use and
what everybody else uses because we're just that contrary.
We've got thousands of undescribed species only known by phrase names.
We frequently in Australia use species names that end up in legislation and are
therefore very hard to change. We have the risk posed by literally thousands
of invasive species that are either in Australia or threatening to arrive.
And there's the increasing importance of recognizing traditional ecological
knowledge as part of the conservation and governance of biodiversity in Australia.
The common thread in all this is a need for a simple common reference point for
researchers, government, and industry, and that purpose has been served by many
years by the National Species List of the Australian Biological Resources Study, or
ABRS for short.
So for much of the ALA's history, we've used the NSL, and the
backbone of the taxonomy that we use in the ALA has been assembled what's been
jokingly called the large taxon collider.
This basically combines that ABRS National Species List with multiple other
sources, including Catalog of Life, the New Zealand Organism Register, and also a
host of other ad hoc changes from many other sources.
The large taxon collider, in all its physical glory, provides a streamlined,
automated process where taxonomic checklists are combined automatically with no
human input. It's a very attractive and extremely efficient way of operating
because it's got fairly minimal human intervention.
However, the success of the collider requires that all input checklists that are
coming from taxonomic checklists
are consistent as possible in the taxonomic hierarchy they use, and that's because
any variance in the hierarchy or authorship will generate errors and duplication as
you produce the taxonomic backbone.
This, of course, affects findability and data matching.
The collider is dependent on incoming checklists having all possible name
combinations for correct matching.
And as we know, all taxonomic checklists are 100% complete, they never have any
errors in them.
But it's a never ending issue for us.
So for example, to give it an Australian example, the common bent-wing bat, which
is a rare and endangered species in Australia, despite its name, was misidentified
for many years as a thing called Miniopterus schreibersii, before it was actually
recognized as an endemic species, Miniopterus aereonoe.
The problem is that because it wasn't actually a synonym, it was never included
in the NSL. So what we had was a situation where we had an endangered
species in the NSL, but the synonym by which most of the records in Australia were
actually known were not actually connecting to anything.
That's not a criticism of the NSL. Our colleagues in ABRS added it as soon as we
found it. The issue is really until we started looking, it was simply unrecognized
as an error in the collider process.
The collider also assumes, and this is important, that the names are placed in a
taxonomic checklist where they need to be for correct data matching, not where they
need to be for taxonomic purposes.
And it's absolutely not the same thing, and I want to make this clear.
For example, having a misapplied name listed both against the taxon that it was
misapplied to, as well as the place where it should be, which is relatively common
in a taxonomic checklist, is a disaster for data matching.
At worst, you're going to end up with a homonym, and at best, you're going to end
up with the record in the wrong place in your taxonomic tree.
Realistically, the idea of automatically building an error-free, human-free
backbone is a fiction.
There's rarely consistency between sources.
There are always nearly errors and omissions, and the focus of taxonomic checklists
is simply not the same as the focus of data aggregators or database managers.
In fact, the inevitable consequence of using a large taxon collider without human
intervention or quality control is demonstrated by what I've got up here.
So this is a previous version of the ALA's taxonomic backbone from a few years ago.
It shows at the very highest taxonomic levels exactly how taxonomic concepts are
jumbled, the units aren't placing correctly,
and there are simple duplications, and it's far worse at lower levels.
And in this version of the taxonomic tree, which is where we started from, there
were over 10 million records, which was 10% of the ALA's data holdings at the time,
that simply weren't matching to anything.
In one case, one scientific name had 78 different variations in the system.
So is that important? Well, I'd argue if you're interested in AI,
or in making your data either findable or reusable, it's pretty important.
And if your focus is actually the best possible representation of biodiversity
data, then there's far too much noise to isolate data quality issues or names
matching issues. So how do you go about fixing it?
Well, we took a systematic three-stage approach, through three successive
backbones. In the first iteration, we looked at trying to
make sure that the input checklists were as complete as possible.
In the second iteration, we identified gaps and filled them.
And in the last iteration, or the latest iteration, we focused on improving the
backbone by looking at data mismatches and no matches, and I'll explain about that
in a moment.
At a high level, our core realization is, as I've already kind of indicated, and
which seems really obvious in hindsight, that taxonomic checklists are not the same
as taxonomic backbones. A backbone is there to display data against the best
available name, not to correctly reflect all the taxonomic decisions and pathways
that have led to that best available name.
Therefore, taxonomic checklists are the essential basis of the system, but they
require intervention by modification in order to display data correctly.
This includes removing or repositioning possibly entirely valid names to improve
data matching. Moreover, critical end uses, such as threatened species assessments
or restricting sensitive species data, also require changes to the backbone.
And to meet those cases, we might need to include informal synonyms such as
spelling errors, populations, or even informal names that aren't actually part of
the taxonomic framework.
We've learned the four important issues for backbones are, firstly, to display
data, you need a single hierarchy.
I would argue that you don't actually need a scientifically valid hierarchy; you
need a single hierarchy. You try to work towards a scientifically valid
hierarchy, but what you need is something that avoids duplication.
The second thing is there's always going to be a need to insert names that are
absent from input checklists. In ALA, we prioritize species in legislation, such as
threatened species, biosecurity species, or restricted access species.
There's also a need to contentiously remove or move concepts that
result in observation records going to the wrong best available name.
And I've already talked about misapplication
Misapplications, but there's also misidentifications and a host of other examples.
Lastly, in certain instances, this may mean overriding the best current name in
order to make sure that the data matches the commonly accepted name.
The biggest innovation we've adopted is metric checking and feedback loops.
We use Checklist Bank
to test versions of our backbone using statistics on issues such as duplicates and
orphan taxonomic units without children.
We match draft taxonomic backbones against our data, and the process of matching
data to our backbone enables us to identify what we call higher matches, where the
name on an incoming observation will only match to a higher point in the taxonomy,
or where there's no matches, i.e., the incoming name won't match to anything.
But they're both basically really valuable guides as to where we need to focus our
attention on from the perspective of improving the backbone.
Most recently, we've extracted a complete set of parameters passed to names
matching. This effectively gives us all 2.06 million names match combinations
between our data and backbone, which basically drives the two processes that I've
just talked about.
So we're still using the code in the large taxon collider.
So the large taxon collider still exists, but what we've done is stopped the
colliding, and we've actually moved to a process where we control our inputs.
We add our sources one at a time using the national species list as the core, and
other elements are added bottom up to minimize duplicates and keep a single
hierarchy. Feedback loops check every step and maintain quality control.
And the proof, as they say, is in the pudding.
So the total number of accepted taxonomic units over the last three years has
reduced from 380,000 to 233,000, which as far as we can tell, is
pretty close to the total number of named species in Australia.
We have less than 1.5% of records affected now by names matching issues, and over
10,000 species that previously had no data now have enough data to actually
get them into public availability.
Over 99% of species listed in government lists in Australia now correctly match to
current scientific names. Moreover, and this has been actually really revealing,
for the first time we've been able to generate reliable metrics on data gaps,
taxonomically, spatially, and
whatever the other one that is that I've forgotten
that basically feeds into our data mobilization program.
So we can actually target our digitization efforts and make suggestions to the
collection sector and the ecological data sector in Australia as to where they
should be focusing their efforts in terms of digitization.
Lastly, we've been able to create a feedback loop back to ABRS to improve what the
national species list by telling them where there are actually issues in the
downstream system from a data quality perspective.
Far be it for me to imply that we've solved everything, we absolutely haven't.
So for that 1.5% of data that's still not matching, we know that at least a third
of that can actually match, and we need to figure out why it's not.
We need to come up with a solution to pro parte synonyms, which in most databases,
what tends to happen is the record ends up on one synonym and not the others.
So how do you actually alert to users that the record that they're looking for
might be under another species?
Homonyms remain our perennial pain, and we're working on a way to improve
our way of handling genetic data as a growing data set.
And lastly, we need a way of handling populations, or at least a term for groups
below taxonomic resolution, which frequently feature in government species lists,
either threatened species lists or sensitive lists.
And just to get a little bit of AI in there, we generated an AI logo for taxonomic
backbone.
That's a post-death metal band called Taxonomic Backbone, in case you're wondering,
you want the AI prompt. Thank you for TDWG for the opportunity to speak today.
And in addition to our many colleagues in ALA, I'd also like to thank the ABRS
team, the many taxonomists who contribute to the ecosystem in Australia, and
particularly Bob Mesibov, who has single-handedly been a massive influence on our
ability to deal with all of this. Thank you very much.
Okay. I don't know if anyone can ask a question that would only give a 30-second
answer, but if you think you can, then put your hand up.
Quentin?
When are T-shirts on sale?
I hope
so.
Do you have one wish list for changes to the nomenclatural codes?
Sorry?
Do you have one thing if you wished to change in the nomenclatural codes, what
would it be?
That's a good question.
Can I think about that?
Look, no. I need to think about
that.
Okay, you'll get your answer later on in the conference. Thanks, Cam.
Okay, so
that's the Australian taxonomy sorted.
So we'll now move on to the rest of the world.
And given the challenges that Cam's just described, it's a wonder that so many
records do match somewhere into
our big infrastructures. So now we're going to move on to Darwin Core, the best
known of the TDWG standards, but not the only one, has underpinned the occurrence
infrastructure successfully for many, many years.
But it's become clear now that with all the new ways that we're collecting data,
that Darwin Core needed a bigger update than the tweaks that the Darwin Core
Maintenance Group have been managing for a number of years.
Sorry, John, you wouldn't describe them as tweaks. They're a bit bigger than that.
But bear with me. So GBIF are now preparing to integrate Darwin Core Data Package
as the next stage, and I welcome Fede and Nicola to tell us about their plans.
Hello, everyone. Sorry if that's too loud.
You need to be wake up anyway. So I'm here with my colleague Nicola Raibek, and
we're going to talk about integrating Darwin Core Data Packages into the GBIF
existing platform.
Let's just get started. One of the challenges that we face in this community is
representing the complexity of biodiversity data in data structure that can capture
as much information as possible.
The de facto standard, the dominant protocol and standard has been so far Darwin
Core Archives. Darwin Core Archive basically is like a zip file.
If you open it, what you get inside is a core file, and then there's
extension files. There's a meta XML that describes how the core file
is related to the extensions, and there's also an EML that describes the dataset
metadata. Right? So
the first message that I want to make with you is that Darwin Core Archives are not
going anywhere. We're going to continue supporting Darwin Core Archives.
So if that data publishing mechanism is sufficient for your needs, just keep using
it, okay?
An independent GBIF 20 year review highlighted that the model of publishing data
around central entities such as occurrences, events, and taxons was not sufficient,
not only to
publish the existing data, but also to engage with new communities.
And that was the reason why we started looking for a new data standard in this
sense.
There are two important milestones that I want to highlight for this year that in
May 26, the Darwin Core Data Package conceptual model
was ratified as part of the Darwin Core standard.
And then the 15th of September, that's less than a week ago, that the
non-descent period after the final review just finished. Okay?
And it's expected by the cohort that the executive
of that week
ratifies the standard and releases the standard.
So
we are super close now to get the standard out.
If you look into a Darwin Core data package, it resembles a Darwin Core archive.
It has data file similar to a Darwin Core archive.
It has an EML, the same EML that you have been using for Darwin Core archives, but
it has now something new that is called the data package.json.
That's something that is borrowed from the frictionless data specification.
And in the data package.json, if I open that file, what I can see is how the data
tables are related between them, but also I can see the specification of those
tables. In this particular example, what we're seeing is the event table.
You can see that it has fields, it has constraints for those fields.
It also specifies how the table is related with our table that's called the
referential integrity, and it also has data types.
I was presenting this to the Living Atlases yesterday, and
I almost get emotional to see that we're going to have a data standard with data
types in it.
So just imagine how that is going to help with some of the data quality issues that
we have seen in the past. Okay, the IPT, the
Integrated Publishing Toolkit, is going to continue supporting Darwin Core data
packages just like it does for CANTA IPT, for Cal IPT, and also for Darwin Core
archives. So the user will be able to upload their files, to map the
data files into the targeted schemas, can also fill the metadata for
both the data package.json and also for the EML.
Then you can validate the archive.
Nikolaj is going to walk us through the validation process, but it's going to be a
more strict validation in terms of data types, completeness of the
data, and referential integrity issues.
And then you can publish the archive.
I just want to highlight there it has a test standard, so this is
enabled only in the test environment so far, okay?
And then I'm going to explain why.
Okay, but so far I haven't said anything what happens with your data.
So I managed to map my archive. I published it into GBIF.
But now what happens with that? In GBIF, we have a data platform that is called the
Data Injection Platform. And basically what it does, it downloads the data from the
sources. It applies a series of data routines
to enhance the data from the spatial point of view with taxonomies like the
category of life, et cetera. And then it feeds some data stores, and that's what
power the data services such as the GBIF API, GBIF downloads, and
the GBIF data portal.
This is only the technical view of the data pipeline.
It also has a human component. We have a group of people giving help desk to the
publishers, and there's also a lot of training material.
We know that the data packages has a richer format to the formats that we expose to
the APIs. But then we think that it's a first step to integrate the Darwin Core
data packages into the existing pipeline, and that's what Nikolaj is going to
explain to us now.
Thank you. Hello. So as Fede was just telling us about, we
have made these new elements-- Is it going? Yeah.
To integrate Darwin Core data packages.
These elements has been, first of all, a new validation method, which has more
validations. We are also including the metadata synchronization, which we already
have existingly, but adapting with the Darwin Core data packages.
And lastly, we have a new ingestion that I'll also tell more about.
And of course, it ends up on gbif.org and other places.
So first step is validation, and for validation with Darwin Core data packages,
there's a lot of different areas which are getting checked.
So as we were shown before, there's a JSON schema checker or a JSON schema file,
the data package JSON,
and that is being checked both to see if it's valid or not.
So of course, we want to have valid schema cells.
We cannot really identify anything.
Then we are looking also into that specific schema file and checking with the TADWG
standardized definitions
to see how they match.
So we are all agreeing on the same standard to use.
Once we are past the schema, we are going in to check the actual data.
So in actual data checks, we are now doing unique constraint checks.
So there can only be a single
this value in an entire resource. We're checking primary key constraints.
We are also checking this new thing with referential integrity, so that whenever
you have something that points to another resource, you are actually guaranteed
that it's there, else our validation will simply not pass.
In addition to this, we're also supplying cell statistics, such as unique column
counts. We're also having information about how many
values are actually present for a given column, so that you have a bit more insight
into your data about, "Was my values actually filled out?" Or what happened with
them.
Once we are past our validation, we then allow our metadata synchronization to
update in our registry, which is controlling how we are downloading things.
This, in turn, helps us to ensure that we are keeping up to date with things such
as title, descriptions, context, licenses, and citations and so forth.
And here, for just the data part, we are primarily using the EML, XML, which I
think most are familiar with.
But there's also a few things where we can fall back to the data package JSON with
the new format.
Lastly, we have ingestions, which is the new part, and also a huge work,
where in this case, we are trying to take the Darwin Core data packages and then
reform it into our internal structure, which allows us to express it on the
gbif.org side on side with the existing Darwin Core archive.
So this, in turn, also allow people to start ingesting Darwin Core data packages
without losing anything,
yet, or you will not lose anything.
But in the future, we'll create new views which allow a richer representation of
your data on the gbif.org site.
And to show part of that ingestion, here's some examples.
My colleagues from data have helped us transform some of these data sets into
Darwin Core data packages.
So here we have the Nice Botanic Garden herbarium as example,
and I've taken some examples here.
So first off, we have a geographical
view where we have some things such as country, we have latitude, longitude,
and other informations.
And that might have been more simple data in the Darwin Core archive, for example.
But with Darwin Core data packages, we now have a list of different resources
that link together in different ways.
So it's not just occurrence getting it directly from event,
but also there's other ways that we could have some material that was pointing to
the occurrence, and then that material was also part of some event.
So you can express how you are attaching data in many different ways, and we will
correctly interpret that and represent it on gbif.org.
There's also more complex cases. Most of them are, unfortunately for me.
So here we have a bunch of information about material mapping, where we have record
numbers-
And we have preparation and other information.
And as we can see, the graph here is starting to grow a bit more, and there's
becoming a lot more relations to this.
So we have all of these different
mappings that needs to be ensured across.
Lastly, I want to show you the media mapping,
where again, it's a more complex graph here.
One thing to note from the Darwin Core archive is that we can now use things
such as a usage policy, which is reused across many different medias because we can
now have a link from media to a usage policy, which was not possible before.
Then,
I think we have some new news.
Yes, sir. So we've been working and thinking what information would be
valuable for someone that published a Darwin Core data package in the GBIF
platform. So this is also enabled only in the test environment, but one of the
things that we have enabled is for
particular data publishers, for authenticated users, we're going to enable the view
of the data validation. And I think that's going to be a great tool to debug
the ingestion process.
This one. Then we've been thinking then how to provide a friendly user interface
for data packages. When you think of data packages, more or less has the structure
of a database with tables, relationships, and so on.
Showing something like that to the user, it wouldn't be so friendly.
So we've been thinking in concise views that the user can just navigate and see the
relationships of those tables in
an easier, more friendly way. Here you can see the navigation at the left side, and
then you can click in one of those tables and see the table detail, navigating the
raw data that has been published. Yep.
Now, what's next for us? What are the plans now?
So first, when I talk with the technical executive, it's going to
release the standard, so we have to align the software components to the official
release of that. We're going to enable the ingestion pipeline and also in the IPP
to publish the Darwin Core data packages into the test environment.
And we're going to invite users to use the test platform and to give us feedback
about that. Then we're going to think of when it's a feasible time to move this to
production.
There's one outstanding issue. The maintenance group for Darwin Core data package
is going to periodically release new versions of that, and then we need to find an
engineering solution on how to keep up with different multiple versions of that.
It's not something new, it's something that we have done, for example, for ABCDE
standards. And then later, that's for next year.
We know that
we're trying to squeeze in data packages into a more strict format.
So we need to start developing the
addition for the new data services around richer data, and that's the work for next
year. And then this is one
of the dreams that we have. This is the...
Don't take it as a compromise that we're going to build that, but it will be
something that we would like to have.
There is some kind of integrated view where you can go and see all the different
types of data published from a richer format, and then you can provide dashboards
with that. And, yeah. So that's it.
Before you say clap, I have one more slide.
I just want to consume all my time because I don't want to answer any questions.
No,
at the beginning of my presentation, I said something about the 20-year review of
GBIF. That basically means that this year GBIF turns 25.
So, please come to our booth and we're going to have there stickers and chocolates
and... We don't have beers, too expensive in this country, but the rest of the
things you can find in there. So thank you so much.
Bribing us with chocolate to get out of answering questions, that's very sneaky,
Freddy.
But we are out of time, so you've successfully done it.
You don't have to answer a question, yet. But come and find them later on.
Okay. Let's move on. So we've heard about cleaning up half a
million names, and we've heard about developing standards that we use to collect
and share the data to the infrastructures.
But it's another thing to turn that work into something a park ranger can actually
use on the ground. So Judith Botha, who's joined us from South Africa, will show us
what happens when that backbone work reaches the people making conservation
decisions on the ground in South Africa's national parks. Thanks, Judith.
Thanks, Ellie, and afternoon, everybody.
So I'm going to take you guys on a quick safari to South Africa.
So keep your hats on because it gets warm.
So just to give you some background about what South African National Parks is.
So really, it was established in 1976.
It has quite a detailed mandate that you can see there on the left-hand side.
But really the important part is that it's supposed to conserve, protect, control,
and manage the national park systems and the biological diversity
throughout South Africa.
So currently we have 21 national parks across South Africa.
The map nicely illustrates those in green, with the blue being the marine protected
areas that we're also responsible for.
So we manage approximately 4.4 million hectares of terrestrial national parks, as
well as around 370,000 hectares of marine protected areas.
So Kruger Park in the top right-hand corner there, that's where I'm based, even
though I work
over all of our parks in South Africa.
It's roughly two million hectares, so that's about the size of Israel, okay?
So to give you a little bit of an indication of the size.
We also turned 100 years this year.
So Kruger Park has been around for 100 years, and we hope to conserve it so that it
can carry on for many more. So I think this map just nicely illustrates the wide
range of biodiversity and biomes that we are responsible for.
So it stretches across the marine, the terrestrial, and the aquatic environments,
together with all the different biodiversity data associated with that.
I saw earlier on, they were looking like on one of the presentations, it seemed
like there was 176 or something animal species in Australia.
Is that correct?
157,000 I think you had on your first graph. Something like that.
Anyway, we have about 67,000 animal species.
But many of our groups are largely unknown, and also a lot of them have a high
level of endemism. So obviously we are very interested in knowing about where they
are and being able to conserve them.
As Ellie mentioned, we have many rangers that work in our park, and we'd like to
present them with tools that they can use to get snapshots and dashboards around
the biodiversity data that they do have in their parks.
So just moving on to what we do have.
So the left-hand side shows that we have a number of scientists that are based in
all of our national parks. So we have a lot of monitoring data that is collected.
So this includes data on field sampling data, sensor data, image data, collar data,
camera trap data. I think everybody in the audience kind of knows what all of that
entails. It also then spans the three different biomes, marine,
terrestrial, and aquatic. But we also have many other stakeholders and partners in
our landscape that we are interested in getting their data as well to make sure
that we can take evidence-based decisions.
So our real problem came to how can we take all of this data and collate it so that
we can come up with ways for rangers and park staff to quickly get a species list.
Also, we are mandated to provide a management park every five years for every park,
and in these management parks, we have to have updated species lists.
So in the past, this was very laborious and very manual, so people went, you looked
for all the literature, you took out all the species data, and then you then
consolidated this and produced an annotated checklist.
So we partnered with the Freshwater Research Centre, they've got a talk later in
the week that you'll hear about, together with their technical partner, CartoSA,
and we developed the BIMS, or the SANParks Biodiversity Information Management
System. So in essence, what this is, it's a central platform to integrate
biodiversity data across all the different areas and to
help us make these evidence-based conservation decisions.
So you'll see we have the taxon groups on the left-hand side there.
So the ones that will be very familiar ones in the top line there, mammals, plants,
birds. So our staff and our park rangers focus a lot of attention on those groups.
But as you get down to the bottom line, you'll see there's things like fungi,
algae, crustaceans, some very strange things, cnidarians, which I don't even know
what they are, worms, bryozoans, et cetera.
Obviously, we are interested in this biodiversity data as well, and we currently
don't have any monitoring platforms to enable us to collect this data.
So we would like to collect the data, get the data from other sources.
So the system really has four features, the first one being the data harvesting and
generating our checklist. The second one are these summary dashboards that people
can pull up. Then we are also interested in looking at our red list species and how
these trends change over time. And lastly, we can't look at species data without
looking at the environment. So if you have your climate data together with your
species data in one dashboard, it just makes it much quicker for people to get the
data and interpret it. So on the left-hand side there on the top, you can see that
we harvest both species data and occurrence data from GBIF directly.
So our species data is harvested from a bigger area.
We then have a much smaller area that contains our reserves, plus a buffer area and
a botany catchment that we are interested to make sure that we are getting all the
GBIF occurrence data. The bottom box shows that we enter then a whole lot of other
data sources, which are unpublished literature, a lot of databases, published
books, reports, theses. So we've got one or two staff members that basically all
they do is they look at literature going back many years, and they actually take
that information out and upload it into our system.
Then the nice thing that we do use is we use the GBIF taxonomic backbone.
So luckily for this audience, I don't need to go into any detail around how that
works, but that's definitely a benefit for us and keeps us making sure that we're
only using the accepted names for our species.
So just to give you an example, so this is a Kruger-based example, and this is what
our BIMS looks like when a manager or a staff member will open it.
So as most web pages have, on the left-hand side, you'll see a number of filters.
So you can filter through from a particular taxonomic group.
It also has spatial temporal filters, and also then about red list status as well
as origin and endemism. So what I'm interested in doing here is to generate a bird
checklist for Kruger. So I've just highlighted the bird, and I've asked for
the spatial filter of Kruger, and then the dashboard gets generated, and
I can then download my annotated checklist.
So this is an Excel version of the checklist.
We also have this available that can be downloaded either as a PDF or CSV.
So you'll see there's categories at the top there.
So we have taxonomic information, then we have things around the species, the
status, the source, the spatial information, and also the record management.
So of particular importance are things like the GBIF coordinate uncertainty, as
well as the coordinate precision.
Some other handy columns is the number of records and when the last or the
most recent record was seen. So that can give us a good indication of is that
species still likely to be in the park, or was it something that was found many
years ago and probably isn't there anymore.
We also then have an include and exclude column, which allows us in the data that
we upload, if we know there has been a misidentification or we think it is, we can
then put in a to exclude, so that next time around when we develop the same species
list, we know that that was an erroneous record, and we don't need to include that
in our checklist anymore. So then just going on to the second feature, which is the
summary dashboards. So you can see there again, that's just the same graph or the
map that I had just now, the bird data, for Kruger National Park.
And then on the right-hand side, you can see there's some graphs that the rangers
can have a look at and download. So just to zoom into a little bit more detail,
you'll see this is one that shows endemism and origin, and then there's also graphs
that show conservation status as well.
So our red list species, what do we want to do with those and how do we track them?
Okay, so this is if we were interested in all the taxonomic groups within Kruger,
this feature gives us a graph and a summary table that shows us what percentage of
our species have the different red list status.
The graph at the bottom is the red list species index that our partner
organization, SANBI, has developed.
So you'll see the different colors on the graph of the different taxonomic groups.
So how the index works is that every time SANBI reevaluates the taxonomic group,
the status may or may not be changed.
And that's why, for example, you can see there's a big dip in the purple line.
That was in the year that it was reevaluated.
The closer the line is to zero means the more species in that particular taxonomic
group are close to extinction. So we would like our lines to be as close to one as
possible. There are several lines at the top of the graph that are just constantly
at one, and those are the taxonomic groups that haven't been evaluated.
So then lastly, just moving on to our climate dashboard.
So as I mentioned, it's really nice to have climatic data available if you are
looking at species distribution.
So this is just some of our climate stations that we have uploaded data.
So really easy for a ranger or park manager just to go in.
You can just find the station of interest.
You then get a series of graphs, you get some summary data, and you
also then get some graphs on the side.
You can see the bottom one, that's just from when the station began to when it
ended. It also has a temporal component, so you can pick out which years or
which dates you're interested in.
And then, of course, the data sets on the right-hand side.
Obviously, a lot of this data is partner data, so it has access
restrictions. But, for our SANParks staff, any of our SANParks colleagues can
actually get this information. So as this week is going around AI and automation,
if we can just pause for a minute and reflect on how both of these were used in
this talk. So firstly, obviously, my friend Chat helped me with some of the
prettier visuals. I do not have a very good brain on that side.
So all the prettiness comes from Chat, but I promise it's all my work.
So just around the data harvesting and the checklist.
So as I mentioned, the data is harvested on a period specific to
particular taxonomic groups directly from GBIF itself.
Then we also have large data sets that are running all the time.
So we have a lot of staff in the field that have collection devices.
These are then entered with different field platforms.
It goes to some software package. We then write scripts and automations to make
sure that we're cleaning that data and that they are ready then for To be entered
into our platforms. Then the assimilation of the species information across the
multiple sources, that's all done by automation.
Our checklist annotations, and then, of course, importantly, our species taxonomy
is verified against the backbone.
Summary databases, many of the information that we get is automatically
assigned values from the particular website.
So all our citers information is drawn directly from there, so nobody has to
re-input that. And then, of course, the generations of the dashboards and the
summaries is all done automatically.
Pretty much the same thing with our Red List Species index.
So we are automatically assigning the values as they come off the different
websites. Then we have this generation of dashboards and summaries.
And then lastly, the generation of the Red List index.
Quite similar for our climate summaries and downloads.
Once again, this automation of these summaries and dashboards so that our staff
don't have to go and reinvent the wheel every time they would like to get a summary
done. So then just in closing-- oh, sorry, hold on. There we are.
So in conclusion, automation and AI have played a large role in ensuring that our
large datasets are integrated and that they ensure us to improve our evidence-based
decision making. So just to
move on to my thank yous, I'd like to just say a big thank you to our
funders. So we had two rounds of funding in this project.
First, the Jaris Biodiversity Foundation gave us a substantial grant, and then the
AFD or the French Development Agency, our partners, Freshwater Research
Commission, as well as Cartoza. Without their big brains, we would never have got
this off the ground. And then lastly, to the funders who've made it possible for me
to be here, of course, SANParks, but then also the Science, Technology and
Innovation Department from South Africa, as well as the National Science Collection
Facility. So thank you for listening.
If anybody is interested, I will be around for the week.
And if you'd like to throw some of your tech at some of our data, please come and
speak to me. We're always open for that. Thank you.
Does anyone have a question for Judith?
Now, it is actually quite hard to hear up here.
Yeah, great talk. I had one question.
So you're collecting a lot of extra data in the field, but do you also publish this
data back to GBIF?
Yes.
Oh, okay.
So some of-- sorry, let me stand here.
So obviously, a lot of our data is protected because of the sensitivity, but we
do publish our data up to GBIF. We've also published all our herbaria collection
datasets up to GBIF. So we have, I think, four or five quite large datasets that go
back many years that are on GBIF. So we are working towards publishing to GBIF as
well as having this as our repository.
Judith, Cindy behind you has a question as well, but she will ask you later.
Okay. Thank you. Okay, moving along.
So we've just seen data standards in action in the hands of conservation managers.
But whilst much valuable biodiversity knowledge comes from our gadgets and sensors,
some of the richest knowledge about species and ecosystems lives in indigenous
communities and is passed down over generations as Marit has already told us
something about earlier today. So Clara Barango Fonseca will show us what it takes
to make space for that knowledge within Darwin Core.
Wow. So we'll see my-
Hello. Good afternoon. A special hello to people that live in South America or from
South America.
So I'm Clara, and I'm from the Brazilian Information System.
I'm going to talk about our work in extending Darwin Core to represent
sociobiodiversity and traditional knowledge in Brazil.
First, I'm going to talk what is sociobiodiversity data.
So according to the Brazilian National Sociobiodiversity Plan from the Ministry of
Environment, Ministry of Social Development, and Ministry from Agrarian
Development, sociobiodiversity data is data describing the interrelationship
between biodiversity and sociocultural diversity, including biodiversity resources,
traditional practices, uses, and knowledge, reflecting the relationships between
biodiversity, indigenous people, traditional and local communities, and family
farmers. But where does this information come from?
So mainly, the most important source is the communities and territories themselves.
Indigenous people in local communities document their own biodiversity uses and
practices, and they are knowledge holders and data owners, and this information
should only be shared according to their consent and decisions in governance.
But we have other forms, other sources of this information.
We can find this information in scientific articles, biological collections, and
museums, often under the term occurrence remarks.
This information could be also found in works by naturalists,
the travelers and naturalists who visit Brazil between the 17th and 19th centuries,
documenting what they observe and learn, and also we can find this information in
market inventories or films.
And
so that's a-- oh, sorry. That's a great, interesting challenge.
We have different kinds of evidence,
different
information produced in different historical context, and it's always a challenge
to see who is the holder of this knowledge.
So for that reason, it was a SES project in 2024, together with
Brazil, Colombia, and Argentina, that we try to develop a data, the first
step, developing a data extension for documenting sociobiodiversity information.
So we had some webinars and in-person workshop that we end up with a
few terms. So terms like use-to, use-to description, use-form,
used-by holder. There was a few terms, one is controlled vocabularies that use
like used-to, organized by used-by type, source type, and other free text, like
used-by holder, use-form, use-to description.
All this information is stored in a GitHub repository.
And the important thing is we're still evolving, discussing, and organizing this
information, but that extension was validated by three
case studies. One was the translation of a book from the 17th
century. The second study case was directly with the community on the
literal of Rio de Janeiro, and the third study was to organize
information of a
living collection of medicinal plants in the botanic garden of Rio de Janeiro.
So these are more or less the results.
So the first one, we had some information gaps.
Used-by holder was missing, used-where was not there, and then we have some
ambiguiting interpretation of terms like used-to.
It's depending who's reading the book and put this information.
We have some
ambiguiting interpretation. Second case study directly to the
community was almost all full, all fulfilled, but we had some publisher
discussion. Who is the publisher of this data? Is it the researcher?
Is it the community? But we know that if we publish through GBIF, the
publisher, it's the most important for the citation tracking.
So what we have to discuss how this set data is going to
cite it and reusing, so who is the publisher again?
The third study case, same things. Used-by type, used-by holder were missing.
But then we move forward. We have another project in Brazil.
It's a GEF project we call Entre Ciências, which means between science.
It's intercultural research, and this project select eight territories,
six in the Amazon and two in the Brazilian Cerrado or savanna.
This project will discuss about data sovereignty and governance for the indigenous
people and local communities. And this project will provide
funding and fellowships to local researchers to identify what they want to
study and monitor. And then we will also talk about data
standards, data use, publishing, data portals.
This project, it starts
two months ago, and it's for three years.
And just to finish the Brazilian context, in Brazil, we have a law, biodiversity
law, which says that all research made by researchers or
companies that have some natural heritage genetic
studies or with biodiversity or associated traditional knowledge, they have to
register this in the national system for the management of genetic heritage and
associated traditional knowledge.
This system will be able to have some mechanisms to benefit sharing between the
companies or researchers and the communities, and we are providing
support on data organization. So we organize a few templates based on
Colombia's templates that we were thinking on
traditional knowledge templates.
And we realized that sometimes it's not species focused.
Maybe it's better to understand that the knowledge is the core and more
important, because sometimes one product or one
knowledge, it's made of several species.
So we did some changes in our templates, and this looks like
the templates of the organizing
associated traditional knowledge. And so what's next?
We have to align control vocabularies and other terms with existing standards to
keep working with our social biodiversity extension.
We will continue working together with Atlas of Living Australia, with the Living
Atlas community, and also with the
task interest group in sensitive data species.
And we also will continue collaboration with indigenous GBIF governance task group,
and we need to increase our engagement with Nedwig and Darwin Core Data
Package.
So thank you all. Thank you, all the organizations that we are working together.
Thank you.
Do we have any questions for
Clara?
No, we have nervous giggles, but no questions. Okay. I'll catch you later, Clara.
Okay, moving along.
So that was a great example of
how standards need to adapt and evolve to represent things that they
weren't originally built for. But our next speaker asks an even bigger question.
Instead of continually stretching our existing systems, what if we designed
biodiversity data infrastructure completely differently from the ground up?
To take us there, I'd like to invite Kit Lewers to the stage. Thanks, Kit.
Okay. Hi. Also, not to scare you guys, I'm not completely tear down everything.
But hi, my name is Kit Lewers. I'm a PhD candidate at the University of Colorado
Boulder. I'm also a NASA CLIMAS fellow/researcher at Goddard
Space Flight Center, where broadly I build infrastructure that can help process raw
sensor outputs to integrate data from remote sensing, biodiversity informatics,
physics, and ecology, where I mainly work on multi-instrument and integrated
platforms focused on optics and spectroscopy.
But this presentation actually deals with quite possibly my favorite vein of
information science, which is what I'm getting my PhD in, and that is information
ecosystems. And it came really from a place of reflecting on my time living and
working in Yellowstone National Park.
And the question that ended up emerging was: what if the way ecosystems respond to
disruption is the way we should design the systems that manage scientific
knowledge? So this presentation actually begins with an analogy and a story about a
woman named Molly Beatty. She was the director of the US Fish and Wildlife Service
beginning in 1993, and she had to make a decision that helped reshape one of the
most studied ecosystems in the world, which is Yellowstone National Park.
And Beatty was a scientist, a lawyer, a public servant, and when she assumed
leadership, she inherited a system that was already deep in conflict.
Ranchers, scientists, policymakers, federal agencies, local communities, and
landscapes were all entangled in competing priorities, and she stood at that
decision point with her team, and that decision was wolves.
So by the early 20th century, wolves had been systematically eradicated from
Yellowstone, and the last resident packs disappeared in the 1920s through hunting
and predator control programs, reflecting an assumption at the time that large
predators were inherently harmful.
So what followed ended up not being a system that was frozen in the wolves'
absence, but one where elk, bison, vegetation, other predators, climate, fire,
hydrology, human management, and more continued interacting.
Removing the wolf had not removed complexity.
It had just removed one set of relationships from an already complex system.
And restoring these relationships meant returning an apex predator to a landscape
from which it had been absent for roughly 70 years while under extreme scrutiny and
opposition. Understandably so, ranchers feared for their livestock.
Communities questioned the necessity.
Scientists could anticipate some outcomes, but they could not specify precisely how
an ecosystem this complex would respond.
But nevertheless, in January 1995, 14 wolves from Canada entered
Yellowstone, with 17 following the next year, and that was 14 animals initially
against 2.2 million acres with no precise model of what was to follow.
And what ended up following became one of the most iconic and maybe most debated
examples of a trophic cascade, which is the process where changes at one trophic
level can propagate indirectly through others.
But trophic cascades are not simple chains of cause and effect.
They unfold within networks. Their effects can be nonlinear, spatially uneven,
delayed, amplified, weakened, and redirected by processes
occurring elsewhere in the system.
So wolves did not simply return and reduce elk populations.
Their return altered predation pressure within a system that also contained other
components. Elk abundance and distribution had changed.
Browsing pressure also changed. And aspen and willow recovered in some places while
not in others. And beaver populations increased, and bison expanded.
And to this day, scientists continue debating the relative importance of these
pathways. And what emerged was not the simple chain of wolves changed elk,
elk released vegetation, vegetation restored the rivers.
There was something infinitely more interesting happening, and that is a network of
interacting responses whose strength and direction varied across space and time.
So no individual wolf contained a blueprint for Yellowstone.
They didn't know how to restore an aspen stand, and no elk knew that it was
participating in a trophic cascade.
System-level change emerged from interactions among these components because
Yellowstone is not only an ecological story, but also a story of systems.
So what Beatty and her team helped enable, and what ecologists have spent the last
30 years documenting, is demonstration that complex systems do not necessarily
respond to interventions in entirely predictable ways.
Change one relationship, and other relationships respond. The system reorganizes.
And an ecosystem, in many ways, is information unfolding in real-time.
So the movement of elk, the growth of an aspen, or the shifting of a riverbank are
physical processes, but each event in the present becomes part of the informational
substrate through which we understand the system in the future via data.
And the same is true of the information systems that we build to study
biodiversity. They operate up to global scales.
They integrate observations across institutions, disciplines, technologies, and
time. And the challenge is not only storing the data, although that is non-trivial.
The challenge is enabling information to move through systems that it was not
originally designed to operate within.
So different institutions, different standards, different tools, different
histories, and priorities, each can occupy something like its own niche.
And each may be internally coherent, but collectively, they form an information
ecosystem, which is interdependent, loosely coupled, heterogeneous, and only
partially coordinated. So once again, that question that ended up emerging is, what
would it mean to design information systems with some of the properties we observe
in complex ecological systems? In an ecosystem,
components
matter because of their interactions.
A change in one place can become an event to which something elsewhere responds.
And system-level behavior emerges not from any single component, but the
relationships among them. So
wolves mattered not simply because wolves were present, but because their presence
restored interactions that had been absent from the system.
Similarly, data does not become valuable simply because it exists in a repository
or an aggregator. Its greater value emerges through interaction.
A new dataset enters an infrastructure. That arrival becomes an event.
A workflow is triggered. A product is updated.
A model can be recalibrated, and now an analysis has become possible.
And other datasets can now acquire new context, and those outputs themselves can
become new events. So information begins to cascade through the system.
And this perspective is what motivates the architectural approach taken in my
research, which is event-driven modular systems informed by microservices
architecture paradigms. In these systems, components are designed to be loosely
coupled but highly responsive. And rather than enforcing one monolithic pipeline in
which every component must change together, microservices allow functions such as
data ingestion, processing, analysis, transformation, and dissemination to operate
independently while communicating through well-defined interfaces, protocols, and
responding dynamically to events in the larger system.
So no individual service contains a blueprint for the entire information ecosystem.
System-level behavior emerges through coordination among them.
So this architecture is scalable not only computationally but sociotechnically.
So new components can be introduced without requiring the entire system to be
redesigned, and different organizations can maintain their own services while
participating in a shared information ecosystem through standards, interfaces, and
event exchanges.
In this way, microservices enable a form of coordination without requiring the
burden of complete centralization.
But loosely coupled, by no means, is structureless.
There remains a necessary layer of shared structure, typically through standards
and governance mechanisms that allow independent components to understand and
respond to one another. So this shared structure does not eliminate difference.
It creates conditions under which difference can coexist productively.
So this is also not entirely foreign to biodiversity informatics.
In many ways, Darwin Core already allows our sociotechnical infrastructure to
behave like a modular system. A natural history museum, the NEON Biorepository,
iNaturalist, and NASA collect fundamentally different forms of evidence, and they
operate under different institutional missions, technologies, and definitions of
expertise. They do not by any means need to adopt the same internal database
protocols, workflows, or organizational models in order to contribute to a shared
information ecosystem. Instead, Darwin Core provides something like a data
contract where institutions can map locally managed information into a
vocabulary that other components of the ecosystem can interpret.
GBIF can then aggregate and expose those records so that researchers can query
across institutional boundaries.
And no single institution needs to be omniscient of the stack that is happening.
So the museum can remain a museum. NEON can maintain its own sampling and
repository protocols. iNaturalist can retain its community-based novel, and their
differences do not have to disappear for the information to become interoperable.
But there is power in making implicit behaviors such as these explicit in
architecture. When we recognize something like Darwin Core as part of connective
infrastructure, we can design more intentionally around it.
We can ask where translation occurs, which assumptions are embedded in those
mappings, and what provenance must be preserved, and who is responsible for
maintaining the interface between systems.
And this allows for biodiversity informatics to remain institutionally diverse
while still functioning in a larger interconnected system.
And as I said in the beginning, in my work, I scale these concepts
to be connected across disciplines while also allowing new additions with far less
friction. So at NASA, before anybody really sees the data, it goes through about
three levels. So that's what the L's are.
L0 is the raw observation and digital numbers that you get off of the sensor, and
L1 is the calibrated radiance, and then L2 is reflectance, which is what people
usually use to get derived products.
So for example, if NASA's remote sensing data that I work with becomes part of GBIF
information, NASA would first need to go through all of this before it even gets to
Darwin Core.
So this allows for including NASA's remote sensing data as an addition and not an
entire paradigm change, because we would not be putting satellite imagery into GBIF
via Darwin Core. We would be using Darwin Core to represent the biodiversity
observations derived from that imagery.
So the challenge then is not to build systems that eliminate complexity.
It's to build systems capable of living with complexity.
Yellowstone did not become a perfectly balanced system following wolf
reintroduction, but it did become a different system with new dynamics.
Conflict between conservation and land use persists.
Management decisions remain very much contested.
Ecological relationships continue changing, and even our scientific interpretation
of what happened has changed as decades of new observations have accumulated.
The intervention did not resolve complexity.
It changed the conditions under which complexity unfolded.
And this is not a failure. This is what system-level change looks like.
And the same is true of infrastructures developed in my work.
Improved data pipelines do not eliminate debates over data ownership, standards,
governance, or interpretation, and new architectures do not dissolve institutional
boundaries. They instead change the conditions under which those boundaries
interact, and they enable new forms of exchange, collaboration, response, and
adaptation. Because the goal has never been to solve the information ecosystem,
it's to create conditions under which the information ecosystem can continue to
evolve. Molly Beatty, once again, and her team did not fix Yellowstone, but what
she did was help restore a relationship that had been removed from it.
Some effects cascaded, others weakened, some occurred only locally, and some became
visible only after years or decades of observation. And that's the model.
Not a static and perfect and complete system, and not a system in which every
outcome must be specified in advance, but systems capable of cascading and
reorganizing as conditions change.
The lesson of Yellowstone is not that one wolf can change a river, but that
restoring infrastructural relationships can change what an entire system is capable
of doing. And my question for my PhD, perhaps obsession if I'm doing it for a
PhD, is what it would mean to build information systems that can do the same for
biodiversity. And with that, I would like to thank all of you very much for
listening. And if we have time for questions, go for it.
And I did take all of these pictures, and I'm very proud of them.
Okay. Any questions for Kit?
You must be proud of them, Kit.
We have no questions? All right, so you can catch Kit later,
and I'm sure you will
because that's a genuinely exciting provocation from Kit.
Data infrastructure that could be built, adapt, evolve in a whole
new way.
Now we're going back to the world of AI, and Niels Reyes is going to show us a
glimpse of that future already in motion with AI-driven monitoring now
running at a scale of tens of thousands of protected sites across Europe.
Thanks, Niels.
Yeah. Let's see.
Well, adding a final flavor to the plate of that rig, and so there will be a little
bit of overlap with previous flavors, especially the lag and also with sand parks.
So I'm the coordinator of the Biodiversity Meets Data project, so the logo is up
there, and I'm going to talk a little bit about mainstreaming high-throughput
biodiversity monitoring using AI.
I will outline my project, then we'll go into the AI, and then I will talk a little
bit about the costs and
expenses on computation that comes with the deployment of AI.
First of all, so Biodiversity Meets Data is a European project, is a Horizon Europe
project, and it's an innovation action, and that's different from a research and
innovation action, and that is that we're going to mainstream existing technology
to new stakeholders. So we're scaling up here across Europe.
It is a European project, and it's a biodiversity explorer for high-throughput
biodiversity monitoring tools, biodiversity data, biodiversity analysis, and for
better conservation across Europe. So I will focus only on the first part today.
Now, these European projects, they come with expectations.
And one of the first expectations from this project is a better monitoring of
biodiversity in the European Union by high-throughput methods, leading to a
better implementation of the nature directive.
So the nature directives in Europe are the habitats directive protecting habitats
and the birds directives protecting birds, and that's implemented in 27,000
Natura 2000 areas, and well, this project extends to the Emerald Network, so UK and
Norway is also in scope together with Switzerland and Ukraine.
Well, then we're covering 30,000 potential areas.
So we're not going to cover them all. This is a pilot study, right?
So now then the next one is a better understanding of the state of nature and the
drivers of biodiversity loss and better uses of existing data.
So a lot of data is still sitting in databases and needs to be mobilized, the same
as was the case in South Africa. If you want to do any trend analysis, you have to
start mobilizing your baseline data.
And then thirdly, that should result in a more complete view of the state of nature
and its evolution. Now, the solution to all this is the
BMD infrastructure, and it looks like this.
So on the left side, we have mostly data mobilization and generation, including the
middle part and the bottom here. So there's mobilizing this data.
So we're generating a lot of data, and on the other side, we're going to use this
data. And so a web history viewer is just visualizing the data.
But then the biodiversity analysis tools in the proposal, those were still called
virtual research environments. Now, for the stakeholders we're working with, VREs
does not resonate. So we rephrased it to biodiversity analysis tools.
Currently, we're in month 19, so we still have quite some time to go.
And there were more or less seven objectives, and I will deal with two of them
today. And this is a very important one.
That is enabling natural resource managers with high-throughput biodiversity
monitoring tools and AI species identification.
So we need AI to scale up this process of monitoring because humans cannot do it
alone. And then we're looking at camera traps, audio devices, and eDNA.
And eDNA, I'm not going to touch on today neither.
But what is important here is that we're going to mobilize all these data to GBIF
because GBIF harmonizes all the data. And then why are we generating this data?
Data generation itself is never a purpose.
You want to do something, you want to analyze it, you want to assess trends, you
want to improve your management, you want to inform policy, and so on.
So we're developing these biodiversity analysis tools for the three realms covered
by the Natura 2000 network, and we co-design these tools with our stakeholders.
So and then what I mentioned, we are doing innovation action and not a research and
innovation action. So the first and foremost stakeholder community for our project
is public and private and third sector managers of natural resource sites, and then
also the policymakers, and in the very end, we have the academia.
So this is not our target group. And then, of course, we develop these tools, and
that aligns very well with what Sand parks has shown.
And we might need to collaborate a little bit more here and to avoid duplication.
So for instance, this is a biodiversity status tool.
On the left side, you see to what directive the species are listed that are
observed, so that the managers of sites get an insight and instant overview of what
their data and their devices have been capturing.
So now, how have these devices have been capturing?
Now, those with camera traps, audio masts, and eDNA.
That's what we're covering with BMD.
And then where traditionally you would go from a camera or an audio device in the
field, and then they start recording, and then you have to start collecting your
data, then you have to transfer it to a laptop, and then you have to start
analyzing the data and do a manual identification.
Where with BMD, where we want to go is that you have a camera trap with a 4G
connection and then a large battery pack or even a solar panel, automated upload,
remote control over your camera, so you can assess whether they're still working or
not, and then data archiving and long-term storage, and then basically an automated
species identification recognition with AI, and then moving these data to GBIF, so
that it's preserved for the future and can be analyzed.
Now, for that purpose, at Naturalis, we have developed a platform that's called
ARISE. And ARISE is an acronym for the Authoritative and Rapid Identification
System for Essential Biodiversity Information.
And then where we're looking at today is this within the red box, a sensors to AI.
That's a digital species identification platform.
So ARISE does more, but at this stage, you're looking at that part.
We have quite a few sensors already deployed.
And the interface of ARISE basically looks like this.
On the left side, you have a navigation panel. Here you see the current deployment.
So although it started in the Netherlands, we're already spreading out, and we're
now scaling up to European scales.
Now, what's important here is that you can upload or receive all your images and
audio recordings through 4G. You can manage your data.
So there's a data management platform.
And then most importantly, we have access to a library of AIs.
So now in orange here, I highlighted all the audio AIs.
Those were recently developed under the Mambo project.
So Quinten already mentioned that one as well. So we have one for birds, bats.
There's several. There's a multi
birds that we have two. Frogs is a new one.
Insects are coming in, and then cicadas and crickets.
And then for the camera traps, we have MegaDetector and SpeciesNet.
There's a Google model. And at Naturalis, we developed the multi-source model
ourselves, and that's
built for citizen science images, but that worked very well on camera trap images
as well, as long as the camera is operating in daylight and not with infrared,
because that makes it a little bit more difficult for this particular algorithm to
identify. But the good thing is you have access to all these different algorithms,
so you can play around with that.
And then next, we have access to three different supercomputer platforms.
Well, and the question here for the users is whether you can wait a night before we
process this data because if you do it on the fly, it's a very costly exercise.
So we
allow that while you get an information, a message.
Well, please come back tomorrow and then check your data.
And then, well, ultimately, you get all your identifications back here.
So this was run with two models. First, we always run the MegaDetector.
MegaDetector is very simple. It's identifying humans, cars, and animals.
So to comply with the GDPR, we have to remove all the humans, and we also have to
remove license plates. So now and then what's left in this case was identified with
the SpeciesNet, and that was identified as a hare, which is correct
Yeah. And then the latest edition, and that was conditional for the BMD project, is
now once this data set has been identified and created, we can export this as
Camtrap data package. And why is that so relevant?
And the Camtrap data package in this community, that's not a new thing.
But this allows all this data to be mapped to the Darwin Core standard, to be
unified and harmonized, and then uploaded to GBIF.
And not only uploaded to GBIF, but we can also map it to the same background
taxonomy. So all this data coming in from all these different centers are mapped
against the Catalogue of Life as it has now been implemented.
And then it serves these biodiversity analysis tools either straight to the API or
through the GBIF snapshots. And then it will drive these species.
Well, this is not a bet. This is one of the first one, and
the likely suspect here by the species distribution modeling to predict the effects
of climate change on the distribution of species.
Because in certain areas, you might want to conserve certain habitats, but due to
climate change, any investment will be a waste of money to try and keep that
particular kind of habitat.
So, that's a bit what we're now implementing across Europe with our stakeholders.
And then the last part is a little bit about how these algorithms actually perform
and what it has costed to develop them.
Now, according to our specialist of the ARISE platform, image recognition is
blazing fast, so that there's 0.03 seconds for one image to be recognized
on a GPU. That's a graphics chip. Or a 0.06 on a CPU.
This was one image from my vegetable plot in Utrecht in the Netherlands, so it will
correctly identify this here.
Sound is slightly more complicated, takes a bit more time to compute, but
here you see one minute recording, and this particular recording identified 10
different vocalizations of birds. This is a very common sparrow.
No, a great tit. Sorry.
So that's a little bit more complicated.
And then going into the costs. So now identifying an image is only a split second,
but teaching it is a little bit more.
So it takes eight seconds per image to actually learn the algorithm to recognize
something.
Now, then the costs. The costs are expressed in the SBUs, and I had to look this
one up. This is not my field of expertise.
But apparently, that's the Stony Brook University quantity, and that's a
supercomputer's internal currency.
Yes. Twice. Okay.
And then we had something on the renting cost.
So one GPU to do the actual computation, that's 120 SBUs per hour.
And if you do it on a high capacity CPU, that's 192 SBUs per hour.
So now depending on the facility, the cost of SBUs differ, but that's a little bit
what you have to keep in mind.
And then, for the training of this multi-source model, which is a fairly complex
model which covers 44,000 taxa and a number of species.
For this data set and the training, there were 42 million labeled images used, and
this multi-source model combines 39 different models.
So mammals are separate from birds.
So there's a higher classifier, and once you have classified it to the higher
level, you go into the deeper levels.
That's how this
model works. This model currently serves 100 million requests per year.
So from citizens science apps, but also from this platform ARISE.
It's available through a high availability auto-scaling web service.
It runs in Naturalis on bare metal servers.
But the training of this one model takes five months training.
So and we repeat that every year. So that's updated yearly.
So it's five months training, one month validation and testing.
And then if you then boil this down to the actual cost, depending on which
supercomputer facility you use, that is between 93,000 to
€130,000 for Snellius, and then 26 to
38 on another one. The advantage of Snellius is that is like an
academic facility that can be used by Naturalis and not for commercial purposes.
So that makes our lives a little bit more easy.
So, this is what I could extract now from the performance, what is needed for these
computers and what the costs are to run these things.
With that, I would like to conclude this presentation.
BMD is a consortium of 14 different partners, among which Quinten and Maïa, of
course, was here. But also Catalogue of Life.
We have an advisory board where GBIF is represented.
So we're working hard on now getting this up and running and really starting
rolling it out. And with that, I would
thank you for your attention. And you can follow us here.
Okay. I mean, it's the questions.
Hey, Tanya. And there's one at the back as well.
Can you hear?
Not online. Not if you're in Australia.
All right.
So there's a glaring kind of-- This is great, and
I think
it would be great to have this planet-wide.
There is an omission, for example, here on invertebrate monitoring, right?
So they're completely, I think, not represented, maybe a little bit through
soundscape. So if I wanted to add the camera
traps that are being developed for vertebrates, that means at this point, I think,
retraining all the models. Are you also keeping
track of what it the cost not only of training models, but
distillation and deployment on devices and the cost of running, so
the energy storage compute on devices themselves and the
trade-offs between those and how you're thinking about it?
Well, I do not have the details of that.
Well, we're looking more in green AI development, that's for sure, with the AI
team. So the team behind the multi-source model and which is applied and well by
various communities and which is also very good for the camera traps.
So we definitely look into that one, but I do not have the details.
And you also mentioned something on invertebrate monitoring? Yeah.
So I didn't really touch on that. So invertebrates in the freshwater and marine
realms and also from malaise trapping, that's mostly done with eDNA
at this moment. So I know from the Mambo project that they have been trying a lot
of things with cameras. For night-flying insects, we have the Avon traps, which get
attracted to the light. Day flying, we have also the Optix cameras.
So they have vertical screens or flat screens.
So for hoverflies, you also always need to have them flat.
So we always have a subset. So that's definitely things that we're working on.
For BMD, it's camera traps, audio, and eDNA for now.
And well, that's as how complicated we go for now. Next project.
Okay, very last question. Up there.
Regarding data reliability, you said you do the
prediction recognition using AI and then push the data into GBIF.
Yeah.
There's one part missing from my point of view.
That's a human in the loop to
say, "Okay, this is the correct identification or not." Otherwise, you flood GBIF
with predictions from the AI that might not be that reliable, especially when it
comes to invertebrates.
How do you deal with that?
No,
excellent point, and that's part of the system as well.
So you have a predictive accuracy.
It's highly recommended to reduce and do filtering.
There's a lot of filtering options in the ARISE platform as well.
Although we want to have a fully automated workflow, I'm not sure whether that's
really realistic. But then the ones with the lower prediction, you would like to
have either the user look at it. As a user, you log into the system, you have your
responsibility of your own data set and also have your responsibility for
publishing. Well, my opinion is there's not a single data set with any errors on
GBIF that can be found, and you can only trace these errors by making them publicly
available, because then people can actually pinpoint you to where the errors are.
And that's where the human in the loop comes in.
There's indeed an option that you can make corrections on wrong identifications and
maybe omit also
low accuracy predictions. And then the last thing, everything we do here is an open
source, open access. All the bets and the code behind the biodiversity analysis
tools will become available.
That's also nice maybe to exchange code with some parks, and because we're all
dealing with the same issues there, right?
Let's not duplicate things too much.
Okay. Thank you, Niels.
That's our tasting plate complete.
From BHL's challenges and its future to data lags, backbones rebuilt, tools in the
hands of practitioners, traditional knowledge, a bold new vision for
infrastructure, and AI operating at a continental scale.
Thank you very much to all eight speakers from our fantastic session.
In my new capacity as editor of BIS, before I let you go, I'm just going to do a
little advertisement. And I want to put in a plug for submitting extended
abstracts for your talks. All of the speakers today have agreed to put in an
extended abstract, so take from their example that all of you speaking over the
next few days are also invited to put in an extended abstract using the Author
platform provided by our publishing partner and conference sponsor, Pensoft.
Thank you very much.
Your session organizers have also been asked to nominate talks that they would
particularly like to see published in BIS to create an enduring record of their
symposium. Some of you will actually be tapped on the shoulder and asked to put in
an extended abstract, but you're very welcome to just do so.
We would really like to have a really great permanent record of the proceedings of
this year's conference.
Now I'm going to send you out into the sunshine.
The mayor is very keen to have us be there on time at 5:00 this afternoon, so don't
spend too much time in the sunshine.
The town hall is that way and a little bit to the left, I'm told, and it's
not a long walk.
With that,
we'll thank the speakers again, and I will see you very soon to have a drink with
the mayor. Thank you very much.